Finding Aid for Taxpayers United Federation Records 1973-1994
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Taxpayers United Federation Records 1973-1994
Taxpayers United Federation.
6 linear feet
Records of Taxpayers United Federation (and the two organizations from which it was formed, Taxpayers Federation of Michigan, and Taxpayers United for Tax Limitation), both organizations concerned with state tax limitation ballot proposals. Board of Director's and president's files, correspondence, clippings, photographs, videotapes, newsletters and other organizational records; contain material concerning ballot drives in 1976, 1978, and 1980.
85430 Bt /2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was donated by Allan Schmid, president of Taxpayers United Federation (donor no. 7009 ) in several accessions during the fall of 1983.
The record group is open for research.
The Taxpayers United Federation, Inc. (TUF) was formed in 1979 when the Taxpayers Federation of Michigan, Inc. (TFOM), led by Allan Schmid, and Taxpayers United for Tax Limitation, Inc. (TUTL)headed by William Shaker, consolidated.
Prior to 1979, both TFOM and TUTL were active in efforts to curb the growth of state and local taxes. TUTL, in particular, was the driving force behind the successful effort to place Proposal C, a tax limitation proposal, on the ballot in 1976. After the ballot failed to carry, the organizations chose Richard Headlee as their spokesman and renewed their efforts. They organized crucial grassroots support and received vital corporate financial backing, such as that offered by Jay Van Andel and Richard DeVos, founders of Amway Corporation. Their diligence paid off in 1978, when Proposal E, designed to place limitations on various local taxes and state taxation and spending, was approved by Michigan voters.
After the 1978 elections, TFOM and TUTL decided to join forces to insure proper implementation of Proposal E. They did so early in 1979. Over the next three years, not only did Taxpayers United Federation concern itself with Proposal E, but also worked to place limits on political terms of office, curb state gas taxes, provide property tax relief, pass the 1980 Tisch tax limitation amendment, and elect Richard Headlee as Governor in 1982.
The Taxpayers United Federation Records are comprised of three series: Taxpayers Federation of Michigan; Taxpayers United for Tax Limitation; and Taxpayers United Federation. Each series is arranged first chronologically by year, then alphabetically by topic. While correspondence in each series is in chronological order by month, the researcher is advised that, whenever possible, correspondence has been left with appropriate topical files.
Subjects:
Citizens' associations--Michigan.; Elections--Michigan--1976.; Elections--Michigan--1978.; Elections--Michigan--1980.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Taxation--Michigan.; Taxpayers United Federation.; Taxpayers Federation of Michigan.; Taxpayers United for Tax Limitation.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Friedman, Milton, 1912-2006; Political elections--1976.; Political elections--1978.; Political participation.; Politics and government--1971-1980.; Tax reform.; Taxpayers United for Tax Limitation.; Taxpayers Federation of Michigan.
Genre/Form:
Cartoons.; Charts.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Taxpayers Federation of Michigan
  Of importance in tracing both the internal and external activities of The Taxpayers Federation of Michigan are the Board of Directors, Clippings, Correspondence, and president's files. Issues of the Talisman, the Federation's journal, are also helpful in explaining the taxation and -spending issues with which the federation was concerned.
  - Undated
    - Bylaws (Box 1)
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Information Bulletins (Box 1)
    - Land Use (Box 1)
    - Local Groups
      - Mecosta County (Box 1)
      - Monroe County (Box 1)
    - Meetings (Box 1)
    - News Releases (Box 1)
    - Organizational Information (Box 1)
    - Property Taxes (Box 1)
    - Schmid, Allan (biographical outline) (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      (includes "Vox Populi-We Hope" by Allan Schmid)
  - 1976
    - Annual Report (Box 1)
    - Attorney General Rulings (Box 1)
    - Board of Directors (Box 1)
      (includes audio tape of organization meeting on October 9,1976)
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Local Groups: Barry County (Prairieville Township) (Box 1)
    - Proposal C (Box 1)
    - State Conferences (Box 1)
    - Sunshine Act (Box 1)
    - Vice-President's File (Box 1)
      (Allan Schmid materials, including correspondence)
  - 1977
    - Annual Reports (Box 1)
    - Attorney General Rulings (Box 1)
    - Board of Directors (Box 1)
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - County Chapter Manual (Box 1)
    - Income Tax Reduction (Box 1)
      includes state senator Gary Byker news release
    - Information Bulletins (Box 1)
    - Local Groups
      - Hillsdale County (Box 1)
      - Mecosta County (Box 1)
      - Organizing Materials (Box 1)
    - Organizing Materials (Box 1)
    - Michigan Citizens For Reasonable Taxation (Box 1)
    - National Taxpayers Union (Box 1)
    - News Releases (Box 1)
    - President's File (Box 1)
    - Property Taxes (clipping, sample protest letter) (Box 1)
    - Questionnaire (unknown if mailed) (Box 1)
    - Single Business Tax (Box 1)
    - State Conferences (Box 1)
    - State Tax Commission (mostly correspondence) (Box 1)
    - Tax Efficiency Association Of Michigan (Box 1)
    - Talisman (Issues) (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - 1978
    - Annual Report (Box 1)
    - Board Of Directors (Box 1)
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Fairs (Box 1)
    - Fundraising (list of contributors) (Box 1)
    - Gas Tax and License Plate Referendum (Box 1)
    - Information Bulletins (Box 1)
    - Legislation (Box 1)
    - President's File (Box 1)
    - Talisman (issues) (Box 1)
    - Tax Limitation Speech Material (Box 1)
  - 1979
    - Board of Directors (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Gas Tax and License Plate Referendum (Box 1)
    - President's File (Box 1)
      (Allan Schmid materials, including correspondence, mostly re: consolidation with TULT)
    - Talisman (issues) (Box 1)
- Taxpayers United For Tax Limitation
  The Taxpayers United For Tax Limitation series includes (like the Taxpayers Federation of Michigan series) records of the board of directors, clippings, correspondence, and president's files. In addition, the finances files shed interesting light on both the types and amounts of contributions to the organization's taxation limitation drives, especially that of 1978. Information on Proposal C (1976) and Proposal E (1978) can be found in their respective folders. (With regard to Proposal E, the researcher should also examine the Taxpayers United Federation, Inc. files.) Finally, the Taxpayers United Research Foundation files contain interesting reports on the two proposals.
  - Undated
    - Ballot Committee (Member List) (Box 1)
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Finances (includes fundraising materials) (Box 1)
    - Taxpayers United Research Foundation (Box 1)
    - Volunteers (includes information packet) (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - 1973
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1974
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Finances (includes fundraising material) (Box 1)
  - 1975
    - Clippings (Box 1)
  - 1976
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Finances (includes fundraising materials) (Box 1)
    - Proposal C (Box 1)
      (folder 1 of 3)
    - Proposal C (Box 2)
      (folders 2-3 of 3)
  - 1977
    - Board Of Directors (re: October 15, 1977 meeting) (Box 2)
    - Clippings (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
      (includes correspondence between Headlee and Henry Ford II)
    - Organization Steering Committee (Box 2)
    - Tax Limitation ("Shaker Amendment") (Box 2)
      (see also 1978 Proposal E)
    - Taxpayers United Research Foundation (Box 2)
      (contains an analysis of why Proposal C lost)
  - 1978
    - Budget (Box 2)
    - Clippings (Box 2)
    - Committee Meeting (mostly re: September 1, 1978 meeting) (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - General (Box 2)
        (includes contributor correspondence and Amway form letter to its distributors supporting TUTL)
      - Fundraising (samples) (Box 2)
    - Finances (Includes fundraising materials) (Box 2)
    - Legal Opinions (Box 2)
    - Newsletters (Box 2)
    - Proposal E (Box 2)
    - Tisch Petition (Box 2)
    - 1979 Taxpayers United Research Foundation (Box 2)
    - 1981 Taxpayers United Research Foundation (Box 2)
- Taxpayers United Federation, Inc.
  The largest of the three series, Taxpayers United Federation, contains valuable information on the Federation's efforts to insure proper implementation of Proposal E, and its unsuccessful attempts to enact term limitation legislation, and reduce property taxes (see respective headings). In addition, material is available on TUF's involvement with Robert Tisch, particularly his 1980 drive to pass his own tax limitation proposal. The newsletter, NEWS, although published sporadically, does for TUF what the Talisman did for TFOM, and can be supplemented by 1979 and 1980 Press Releases. Both General and Executive Director Correspondence (which includes that from contributors); Board of Directors; Committees (Executive, Finance, Property Tax), and Finances files are vital to understanding the internal workings of the Federation.
  - Undated
    - Board Of Directors (Box 2)
    - Bylaws (Box 2)
    - Clippings (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - General (Box 2)
      - Executive Director (Ken Nyquist)
        - Schmid, Allan (Executive Vice-President, TUF) (Box 2)
        - Shaker, William (Chairman, TUF) (Box 2)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Drafts (mostly solicitations) (Box 2)
    - Executive Board (address roster) (Box 2)
    - Finances (Box 2)
    - Handbook (Box 2)
    - Local Groups
      - Organizational Material (Box 2)
      - Tax Limitation By Region (Box 2)
    - Michigan State Legislature (Box 2)
    - National Tax Limitation (Box 2)
    - News (typed article for undated issue) (Box 2)
    - Organization Information (Box 2)
    - Petitions, Miscellaneous (TUF and outside organizations) (Box 2)
    - Press Releases (Box 2)
    - Property Taxes (Box 2)
    - Proposal E (Box 2)
    - Solicitation Letters (samples) (Box 2)
    - Term Limitation
      - General (Box 2)
      - Clippings (Box 2)
    - Tisch, Robert (clipping, 1980) (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - 1977 Term Limitation (clippings) (Box 2)
  - 1978
    - Ballot Tax Proposals (Senate Fiscal Agency) (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Proposal E (Box 2)
    - Term Limitation (clippings) (Box 2)
  - 1979
    - Board of Directors (Box 3)
    - Budget Bylaws (Box 3)
    - Campaign Finance Statements (Box 3)
    - Clippings (Box 3)
    - Committee Rosters (Box 3)
    - Correspondence
      - General
        (includes samples of solicitation letters sent by Van Andel and DeVos on behalf of TUF)
        - January-April (Box 3)
        - May-August (Box 3)
          (includes letter from Amway Director Black confirming contribution to TUF)
        - September-December (Box 3)
      - Executive Director (Ken Nyquist)
        - Barrett, Jim (Treasurer, TUF) (Box 3)
        - Black, Noel (First Vice-President, TUF; Director (Box 3)
        - Public Affairs, Amway Corporation) (Box 3)
        - Board of Directors (Box 3)
        - Dykema, Charles (Secretary, TUF) (Box 3)
        - Headlee, Richard (President, TUF) (Box 3)
        - Michigan State Legislature (Box 3)
        - Representatives (Box 3)
        - Senators (Box 3)
        - Schmid, Allan (Executive Vice-President, TUF) (Box 3)
        - Shaker, William (Chairman, TUF) (Box 3)
        - Welty, Joel (Second Vice-President, TUF) (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
      - McMasters Associates (public relations firm) (Box 3)
    - County Treasurers (Box 3)
    - Executive Committee (Box 3)
    - Finance Committee (Box 3)
    - Finances (includes ledger handbook, and contains later material) (Box 3)
    - Gas Tax (Box 3)
    - Intangible Tax (Box 3)
    - Legislation (re: taxation and spending)
      - House Bills
        - 4166 (Box 3)
        - 4232 (Box 3)
        - 4232 Amendments (Box 3)
        - 4276 (Box 3)
        - 4700 (Box 3)
        - 4716 (Box 3)
      - Senate Bills
        - 252 (Box 3)
        - 460 (Box 3)
        - 460.1 (Box 3)
        - 460.2 (Box 3)
        - 528-531 (Box 3)
    - Local Group
      - Berrien County (meeting announcement) (Box 3)
      - Dickinson County (Box 3)
      - Glen Arbor (letter re: establishment of organization) (Box 3)
      - Holland (Box 3)
      - Iron County (Box 3)
      - Macomb County (County. Equalization Report) (Box 3)
      - Organizational materials (Box 3)
      - Ontonagon County (Box 3)
      - Saginaw United Taxpayers (Box 3)
      - Tri County (Montcalm, Ionia, Kent) (Box 3)
      - Upper Peninsula (two issues of the "U.P. Landowner") (Box 3)
      - Washtenaw County (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Membership (Box 4)
    - National Tax Limitation Committee (Box 4)
    - Newsletter (Box 4)
    - Petitions, Miscellaneous (TUF and outside organizations) (Box 4)
    - Press Relations (includes letters to various editors) (Box 4)
    - Press Releases (Box 4)
    - Property Tax Committee (Box 4)
    - Property Tax Relief. (Box 4)
    - Proposal E (includes material re: the implementation of the proposal), 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Questionnaire (samples of returns) (Box 4)
    - Siljander Proposal (Box 4)
    - Single Business Tax (Box 4)
    - Solicitation Letters (Box 4)
      contains analysis of responses received
    - Talisman Committee (Box 4)
    - Term Limitation (clippings) (Box 4)
    - Welty, Joel (Application for executive directorship) (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - 1980
    - Attorney General (Box 4)
    - Ballot Tax Proposals (Box 4)
      includes Milliken-Crim, and Tisch proposals
    - Board Of Directors (Box 4)
    - Budget (Box 4)
    - Clippings (Box 4)
    - Correspondence
      - General
        - January-June (Box 4)
        - July-December (includes several Amway-TUF letters) (Box 4)
      - Executive Director (Ken Nyquist)
        - Barrett, Jim (Treasurer, TUF) (Box 4)
        - Black, Noel (First Vice-President, TUF; Director, Public Affairs, Amway Corporation) (Box 4)
        - Boards of Directors (Box 4)
        - Contributor Correspondence (Box 4)
        - Dykema, Charles (Secretary, TUF) (Box 4)
        - Executive Committee (Box 4)
        - Headlee, Richard (President, TUF) (Box 4)
        - Michigan State Legislature (Box 4)
        - Representatives (Box 4)
        - Senators (Box 4)
        - Schmid, Allan (Executive Vice-President, TUF) (Box 4)
        - Shaker, William (Chairman, TUF) (Box 4)
        - Welty, Joel (Second Vice-President, TUF) (Box 4)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Executive Committee (Box 4)
    - Finances (Box 4)
    - Initiatives and Referendums (material re: process) (Box 4)
    - Limited Government Committee (Box 4)
    - Local Ballot Question Committees (Secretary of State bulletin) (Box 4)
    - Local Groups: Dickinson County (Box 5)
    - Michigan State Legislature (Box 5)
    - National Tax Limitation Committee (Box 5)
    - Organization Information (Box 5)
      (contains brief but informative history of TUF)
    - Petitions, Miscellaneous (TUF and outside organizations) (Box 5)
    - Press Relations (includes letters to various editors) (Box 5)
    - Press Releases (Box 5)
    - Property Tax Committee (Box 5)
    - Property Tax Relief
      - General (Box 5)
      - Drafter's Notes (Box 5)
    - Proposal E (Box 5)
    - State Chamber of Commerce (Box 5)
    - Talisman (Box 5)
      mostly drafts of articles
    - Term Limitation
      - General, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Clippings (Box 5)
      - Publicity File (includes earlier material) (Box 5)
      - Research File (includes earlier and later material) (Box 5)
    - Tisch Amendment (Box 5)
      (see also 1980 Ballot Tax Proposals)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - 1981
    - Board Of Directors (Box 5)
    - Brown, Thomas H., state representative (Box 5)
      (mostly correspondence, includes later material)
    - Citizens Research Council (Box 5)
    - Clippings (Box 5)
    - Correspondence
      - General (Box 5)
      - Executive Director: Miscellaneous (Joel Welty) (Box 5)
      - Executive Vice-President (Charles Dykema) (Box 5)
    - Drafting Committee (Box 5)
    - Executive Committee (Box 5)
    - Initiatives and Referendums (material re: process) (Box 5)
    - Local Groups: Saginaw (Box 5)
    - Michigan State Legislature (Box 5)
    - National Tax Limitation Committee (Box 5)
    - NEWS (TUF Newsletter) (Box 5)
    - Petitions, Miscellaneous (TUF and outside organizations) (Box 5)
    - Property Tax Relief (Box 5)
    - Questionnaire (Box 5)
      (samples of returns, and includes later material)
    - Saginaw
      - City (Box 5)
      - Center and Commons (Box 5)
    - Solicitations (Box 5)
    - Term Limitation (Box 5)
    - Tisch, Robert (Box 5)
    - Welborn, Jack (State Senator) (Box 5)
    - Welfare Limitation (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - 1982
    - Board of Directors (Box 5)
      (agenda for January 1, 1982 meeting, and call to April 5, 1982 meeting)
    - Budget (Box 5)
    - Citizens Research Council (Box 5)
    - Citizens to Remove Dalton (Saginaw city manager) (Box 5)
    - Clippings (Box 5)
    - Correspondence
      - General (Box 5)
      - Executive Director: Miscellaneous (Joel Welty) (Box 5)
    - Headlee Endorsement (Box 5)
    - Initiatives and Referendums (material re: process) (Box 5)
    - Local Groups: Saginaw (Box 5)
    - NEWS (TUF Newsletter) (Box 5)
    - Property Tax Credit Bill (Box 5)
    - State Chamber of Commerce (Box 5)
    - Tax Freeze Amendment (includes earlier materials) (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - 1984
    - Annual Report (Box 5)
  - 1994
    - TUF vs. William D. McMaster, 8 folders (Box 6)
      (re: use of name)
- Visual Materials
  Photographs of active members and meetings; slide presentation relating to a 1978 ballot proposal; two video tapes relating to a 1976 ballot proposal; and a video tape of Milton Friedman discussing a national tax limitation proposal.
  - Taxpayers United for Tax Limitation Certificate of Recognition awards May 1974
    - A-M (Box 6)
    - N-Z (Box 6)
    - Individuals (Box 6)
  - Taxpayers Federation of Michigan Meeting at East Tawas 1977 (Box 6)
  - "Michigan Needs Tax Limitation" (Taxpayers United for Tax Limitation) 1978
    - Slide presentation, 80 slides (Box 6)
    - Text (Box 6)
  - Proposal C debates 1976, U-matic videocassettes
    - Shaker v. Drake, WKAR-TV (Box 6)
    - Shaker v. Noonen, WCUM-TV (Box 6)
  - National Tax Limitation Committee, Milton Friedman discussing tax limitation proposal, late 1970s, U-matic videocassette (Box 6)